Artifact Collection AC
Tufts Archival Research Center
- Cuneiform, scarabs, memorial slab, and tomb figure, circa 2150 BCE -- 0100 CE; AC.003.000002; 8 Artifact(s)
  - Clay cone, cuneiform, circa 2150s -- 2110s BCE; AC.039.00006 (Box 39)
    Top tray. The Well-Preserved Cone: Introduction: This cone is written in Sumerian and uses the cuneiform script. In ancient Mesopotamia, clay cones were often buried as foundation deposits for temples or palaces. Only gods were supposed to read them. This cone can be dated to the late 22nd century BCE, slightly before or contemporary with the Ur III period. Judging from its content, it must have been excavated at the site of Tello, situated in the South of raq today and the central part of a city-state named Lagaš. This text is a typical royal inscription, usually recording what a ruler does to please his god(s), so that the effort of the ruler can be recognized and reciprocated. 1. dnin-gír-su 2. ur-sa? kalag-ga 3. den-líl-lá-ra 4. gù-dé-a 5. énsi 6. lagaški-ke4 7. ní?-du7-e pa mu-na-è 8. é-ninnu dIM.DUGUDmušen-bábbar-ra-ni 9. mu-na-dù 10. ki-bi mu-na-gi4 Translation: For Ningirsu (tutelary god of Lagaš), valiant warrior of Enlil (head of the then pantheon), Gudea, governor of Lagaš, made things splendid as they used to be, built the temple Eninnu, his (=Ningirsu's) white thunder-bird (a metaphor referring to the temple), and restored it to its place. Identified and translated by Xiaoli Ouyang, a Ph.D. student working at the Harvard Semitic Museum, March/April 2006. Because the cuneiform cone had never been clearly identified or translated (information was based on what the donor, J. Welch had sent with the items), Susanne Belovari, archivist for reference and collections, asked the Semitic Harvard Museum to identify and transcribe this and all other cuneiforms. late 22nd century, BCE
  - Clay tablet, cuneiform (Sumerian), circa 2112 -- 2004 BCE; AC.039.00007 (Box 39)
    Top tray. The Biggest Tablet: Introduction: This tablet is written in Sumerian and uses the cuneiform script. It can be dated to the Ur III period, but except for this, no further information about dating is available. As for provenance, it should come from southern Mesopotamia. It seems to deal with withdrawal of flour, butter, beer and beer-related material from warehouses located in different places. Obv. 1. […] zì-kala [X liters] of kala-flour 2. […] sìla zú-lum X liters of dates 3. […] eša 2 (bán) […] X (liters) of eša-flour (and) 20 liters of … 4. […] ?sìla? ì-nun 2 sìla ?kaš!? […] X liters of butter and 2 liters of beer 5. 1 sìla ?eštin-babbar 1 sìla kaš! še 1 liter of white wine and 1 liter of barley beer 6. 1 (bán) kaš! sig5 1 (bán) kaš!-ge6 ?sig5? 10 liters of high-quality beer and 10 liters of high-quality beer 7. šà é-duru5 ZÌ (from) the village; 8. 3 (bán) zì-kala 5 sìla zú-lum 30 liters of kala-flour and 5 liters of dates 9. 1 (bán) eša 2 (bán) zì še 10 liters of eša-flour and 20 liters of barley flour 10. 1 sìla ì-nun 1 sìla kaš sig7 1 liter of butter and 1 liter of malted? beer 11. 1 sìla kaš! še 3 (pi) 2 (bán) dida ?in-a 1 liter of barley beer and 200 liters of ordinary malt 12. šà kisal from the Courtyard; 13. 2 (bán) zì-kal 2 sìla zú-lum 20 liters of kala-flour and 2 liters of dates 14. 2 sìla eša 3 sìla zì-še 2 liters of eša-flour and 3 liters of barley Flour 15. 1/2 sìla ì-nun 1/2 sìla kaš!-sig7? Half a liter of butter and half a liter of malted beer 16. 1/2 sìla kaš! še 3 (pi) 1 (bán) dida ?in-a Half a liter of barley beer and 190 liters of ordinary malt 17. ki ki? […] A AŠ from…; 18. 2 (bán) ?eša? […] zì še 20 liters of eša-flour X …barley flour The reverse is too broken to read. Identified and translated by Xiaoli Ouyang, a Ph.D. student working at the Harvard Semitic Museum, March/April 2006. Because the cuneiform cone had never been clearly identified or translated (information was based on what the donor, J. Welch had sent with the items), Susanne Belovari, archivist for reference and collections, asked the Semitic Harvard Museum to identify and transcribe this and all other cuneiforms. Date is approximate: 2112-2004 BCE
  - Tomb figure of Pharaoh Setekhy I, circa 1375 -- 1202 BCE; AC.039.00009 (Box 39)
    Top tray. Documentation (in file) has history of Egypt, ca. 1375-1202 BC.
  - Clay cone, cuneiform (Akkadian), circa 1934 -- 1924 BCE; AC.039.00010 (Box 39)
    Top tray. The Largely Reddish Cone: Introduction: This text uses the cuneiform script and is written in Akkadian, the earliest attested Semitic language. It can be dated to the reign of Lipit-Ištar (ca. 1934-1924 BCE), a ruler of the city-state Isin during the Isin-Larsa period, when various local powers in southern Mesopotamia proper and on its periphery fought with each other for hegemony after the collapse of the Ur III dynasty. This period ends when Hammurabi reunited southern Mesopotamia around 1750 BCE and brought the Old Babylonian Kingdom to its heyday. The signs on this cone are too broken to read. But based on parallels, the text supposedly records that Lipit-Ištar fashioned a pair of pot stands dedicated to the god Enlil and goddess Ninlil, the leading couple of the then pantheon. Identified and translated by Xiaoli Ouyang, a Ph.D. student working at the Harvard Semitic Museum, March/April 2006. Because the cuneiform cone had never been clearly identified or translated (information was based on what the donor, J. Welch had sent with the items), Susanne Belovari, archivist for reference and collections, asked the Semitic Harvard Museum to identify and transcribe this and all other cuneiforms. Date is approximate: 1934-1924 BCE
- Manuscript, printed, and book history materials, circa 0100 -- 2007; AC.004.000002
  This series contains manuscripts, prints, and book history materials dating circa 0100 – 2007. Manuscripts includes documents written on papyrus, illuminated manuscript leaves, leaves from religious texts, corresondence, and speeches. Printed material includes governmental records from the US, Britain, and Russia; leaves from religious texts as well as early printed books, some with woodblock illustrations; correspondence; and newspapers. There are also hand-drawn and printed maps, as well as illustrative and photographic prints. The book history material consists of type-writers and book binding material.
  This series is arranged into 10 sub-series: Autographed letters collection; Book history materials; Ephemera; Government records; Illuminated and early manuscripts; Manuscripts; Maps; Papyrus; Printed materials; and Prints.
  - Autographed letters collection, circa 1812 -- 1965; AC.004.001
    This sub-series contains correspondence and photographs signed by notable figures dating circa 1812 – 1965. People of note represented in this sub-series include Albert Einstein, Charles Dickens, and Jack London.
    This sub-series is arranged roughly alphabetically.
    - Ina Donna Coolbrith, circa 1907; AC.011.00011 (Box 11)
    - Charles Dickens correspondence and prints, circa 1869; AC.011.00006 (Box 11)
    - Albert Einstein correspondence, 1934; AC.011.00009 (Box 11)
    - William Faulkner correspondence, 1961; AC.011.00004 (Box 11)
    - Henry James condolence letter, 1910; AC.041.00013 (Box 41)
    - Jack London correspondence and photograph, 1885 -- 1928; AC.011.00002 (Box 11)
    - Jack London letter, circa 1906; AC.041.00008 (Box 41)
    - Edwin Markham correspondence and signed printed copy of "Lincoln, the Man of the People", circa 1919 -- 1922; AC.011.00007 (Box 11)
    - "Original autograph letter by John Ruskin presented with the library edition of Ruskin's works", circa 1877 -- 1912; AC.041.00009 (Box 41)
      Gift of James F. Perkins, class of 1924.
    - Booth Tarkington correspondence and print, circa 1900; AC.011.00005 (Box 11)
    - William Thackeray correspondence and print, undated; AC.011.00003 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence between notable persons and Tufts, circa 1821 -- 1965; AC.023.00001 (Box 23)
      This folder contains original manuscript and copies of correspondence from minor luminaries such as John F. Kennedy, Marie Curie, Herbert Hoover, and Mary S. Livermore to Tufts affiliated people such as Henry W. Holmes, John Albert Cousens, and Joseph Homidar.
    - Photographs of notable men, circa 1840 -- 1900; AC.023.00002 (Box 23)
      This folder contains photographs and prints, some signed, of several minor luminaries such as Phillips Brooks, Schuyler Colfax, and George S. Boutwell.
  - Book history materials, circa 1819 -- 1960; AC.004.002
    This sub-series contains typewriters and book binding materials dating circa 1819 – 1960.
    - Swiss organdy material, used for binding books, circa 1891 -- 1930; AC.017.00016 (Box Shared 9)
      Top tray.
    - Remington quiet-riter typewriter with miracle tab, 1950 -- 1960; AC.053 (Box Shared 13)
      In heavy tweed patterned case with attached key. Found uncataloged in the stacks in the winter of 2009. Speculation that it was John Holmes's typewriter at one time, but the provenance is unclear.
    - Hammond multiplex typewriter, 1923 -- 1927; AC.054 (Box Shared 13)
      In wooden case. Found uncatalogued in the stacks in the winter of 2009. User manual, instructions, and spare parts were also found with the typewriter. The provenance is unclear.
  - Ephemera, circa 1893 -- 1898; AC.004.003
    This sub-series contains printed ephemera dating circa 1893 – 1898. This includes a postcard and ticket from the World's Columbian Expositions dated 1893; four Apache playing cards dated circa 1898; and stamps illustrating the Stamp Act, undated.
    - The World's Columbian Exposition postcard and ticket, 1893; AC.011.00008 (Box 11)
    - Apache playing cards, circa 1898; AC.011.00014 (Box 11)
      Gift of Dr. E. C. Skinner, 1898.
      Label reads, "Location: Detroit. Article: Indian Playing Cards. No. 2051. Taken from body of dead Indian."
    - Stamps Illustrating the Stamp Act, undated; AC.011.00015 (Box 11)
  - Governmental records, circa 1600 -- 1945; AC.004.004
    This sub-series contains governmental records from Great Britain, Russia, and the United States dating circa 1600 – 1945. These records include royal declarations and proclamations from Great Britain; a Russian military order; American WWII bond posters and WWI military envelopes; a Massachusetts treasury certificate; American documents describing land ownership; and a complaint and warrant filed against David Kelly in Kingston, New Hampshire.
    This sub-series is arranged chronologically.
    - Manuscript fragment, King James of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland to Sheriff of Worcester letter, circa 1600; AC.040.00002 (Box 40)
      Translation included in folder.
    - Declaration of William, Prince of Orange, for keeping peace in Scotland, 1689-02-06; AC.012.00003 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 5)
    - George III proclamation of Jonathan Bowman as Justice of the Peace, 1765; AC.042.00002 (Box Shared 15)
    - Benjamin Webster's complaint and warrant against David Kelly, Daniel Colcord, etc. for riotous assualt, Kingston, N.H., 1772; AC.042.00006 (Box Shared 15)
    - State of Massachusetts Bay treasury certificate, 1780; AC.041.00005 (Box 41)
    - Baptiste Marlet's patent for 500 acres in Clinton Co., NY, 1790; AC.041.00019 (Box 41)
    - Signed George Washington document, 1793; AC.012.00001 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 5)
      George Washington
    - Russian military order, circa 1830; AC.041.00002 (Box 41)
      From original housing: "A Russian military order, given me by Capt. McMaster (?), who picked it up on the Battlefield of Balaclava (Crimean War). Capt. M. was there and got a number of Russian relics."
    - Military correspondence, circa 1830s -- 1840s; AC.040.00024 (Box Shared 5)
      Currently unidentified; found in the Ryder collection which before re-processing in 2012 had come to include many non-Ryder items. Susanne Belovari made photocopies of letters to identify them at home.
    - Memoranda Relating to Alaska Territory, circa 1880; AC.020.00008 (Box 20)
    - World War I envelope, 1916; AC.041.00003 (Box 41)
    - Department of the Treasury World War II bond posters, 1941 -- 1945; AC.027.00003 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 6)
      Posters removed from map case (room 10), drawer #29. "That Liberty Shall Not Perish from the Earth by Liberty Bonds forth Liberty Loan" [decapitated statue of Liberty on orange background]. Russian Poster 1945 [Russian soldier with red flag burying yellow star standing over deceased Nazi soldier].
  - Illuminated and early manuscripts, circa 0900 -- 1600; AC.004.005
    This sub-series contains illuminated and early manuscript leaves from religious texts dating circa 0900 – 1600.
    - Mt. Athos codex, Greek Gospels, Greek uncials, circa 0900 -- 1000; AC.040.00017 (Box 40)
    - Leaf from Latin codex Gospels, Carolingian uncials, 1000; AC.040.00007 (Box 40)
    - Greek manuscript leaves, circa 12th century; AC.040.00003 (Box 40)
      Original casing: "Kichbungen (sp. ?) liturgizche, griechisch, 12 jahrh (?)"
    - Bible leaf, 1200; AC.040.00006 (Box 40)
    - Double manuscript leaf, Flemish, 1280; AC.042.00007 (Box Shared 15)
      From Welch collection.
    - Manuscript leaf with decorated initial, Italian, 1375; AC.040.00016 (Box 40)
    - Illustrated music score-manuscript leaf (fragment?), 1400; AC.042.00003 (Box Shared 15)
    - Manuscript leaf with capitals, 1400; AC.042.00004 (Box Shared 15)
    - Glossed manuscript leaf, 1400 -- 1500; AC.040.00009 (Box 40)
    - Illuminated manuscript leaves from the Book of Hours, France, circa 1400 -- 1499; AC.046 (Box 46)
    - Antiphonal manuscript leaf, Paris, 1430; AC.042.00005 (Box Shared 15)
    - Illuminated vellum leaf from Book of Hours, 1450; AC.040.00023 (Box 40)
    - Illuminated manuscript leaf, 1500; AC.040.00014 (Box 40)
      Possibly from girdle book.
    - Book of Hours miniature, Italy, circa 1500; AC.040.00018 (Box 40)
      Mat "Reference: "Italian Miniatures" by Prof. Mario Salmi.
    - Miniature from an Italian antiphonal, 1500; AC.040.00019 (Box 40)
      Mat: reference "Italian Miniatures" by Prof. Mario Salmi. Miniature cut from page.
    - Illuminated Book of Hours page, Paris, 1500; AC.040.00021 (Box 40)
    - Illuminated Book of Hours pages, 1500; AC.040.00022 (Box 40)
    - Illuminated manuscript leaf from Book of Hours, depicting St. Anthony of Egypt, circa 16th century; AC.040.00015 (Box 40)
  - Manuscripts, circa 1698 -- 1999; AC.004.006
    This sub-series contains manuscripts written circa 1698 – 1999. These manuscripts mainly consists of correspondence dating circa 1698 – 1891. Also included in this subseries are a Fourth of July speech dated 1813; fragments of a journal dating 1774 and a report dating 1860; an "I owe you" document dating 1772; two handwritten lists dating circa 1780 – 1860; a copy of a prophecy by Mother Shipton (1488 – 1561) dating circa 1862; and a page from a Patrick family Bible dating circa 1775 -- 1809. There is also a Megillah scroll written in Hebrew from the 19th or 20th century.
    This sub-series is arranged roughly chronologically.
    - British letter, circa 1698 -- 1699; AC.041.00004 (Box 41)
    - Dawson letter, circa 1715; AC.020.00013 (Box 20)
    - Mathew Bryant "I owe you" to John Dudley on behalf of Jacob Currier, 1772; AC.041.00001 (Box 41)
      Original housing note: "Writ and documents in case of Jacob Currier, who in 1792 was fined 4 shillings for profane swearing by Josiah Bartlett J.P. J. B.'s autograph (signer of Decl. of Ind.)
    - Correspondence and manuscript leaves, circa 1772 -- 1810; AC.020.00006 (Box 20)
    - Fragments of documents and letters, circa 1739 -- 1793; AC.041.00006 (Box 41)
    - Extract from the journal of Thomas Hutchinson, circa 1774; AC.041.00012 (Box 41)
    - Page from a Patrick family Bible, 1775 -- 1809; AC.041.00014 (Box 41)
    - Original proprietors in Templeton, MA, circa 1780 -- 1850; AC.020.00003 (Box 20)
    - Fourth of July speech manuscript, 1813; AC.020.00007 (Box 20)
    - Letter by Blodgett to Mr. Miner grant, 1826; AC.041.00011 (Box 41)
    - Fragment of a report about Guiseppe Mazzini, 1860; AC.041.00025 (Box 41)
      The fragment was found in the former Ryder collections in 2011: processing of the socalled Ryder collection revealed that over decades historical material was added to the Ryder collection rather arbitrarily. When reprocessing the Ryder archives, material that was clearly not related to the Ryder donation, was pulled and either formed new collections or added to the AC collection when we had absolutely no information about provenance; processed by Susanne Belovari May 2012. Date is approximate since the last page mentions his actions in 1860 and uses the present tense to describe Mazzini's behavior and Mazinie died in 1872. 12 page handwritten fragment, missing first page/s and perhaps missing last page/s summarizing Mazzini's achievements and actions from at least 1832 to 1860. Giuseppe Mazzini (1805-1872) was an Italian poilticians, journalist and activist and detrimental in unifying Italy and supporting movements for popular democracy.
    - Handwritten list, circa 1860; AC.020.00017 (Box Shared 5)
      The fragment was found November 29 2005 when Tisch Library staff completed their research for a civil war related exhibit. List of historical items such as album of Continental Currency or lottery ticket Harvard College 1794. We are unable to ascertain provenance of list and therefore added it to AC/ collection; Susanne Belovari, Archivist for Reference and Collections, October 2012.
    - Mother Shipton's prophecy, circa 1862; AC.041.00024 (Box 41)
      Date is approximate. The prophecy was found in the former Ryder collections in 2011: processing of the socalled Ryder collection revealed that over decades historical material was added to the Ryder collection rather arbitrarily. When reprocessing the Ryder archives, material that was clearly not related to the Ryder donation, was pulled and either formed new collections or added to the AC collection when we had absolutely no information about provenance; processed by Susanne Belovari May 2012. Handwritten copy of a fake prophecy first published in 1641, 80 years after the death of Ursula Southill [Ursula Soothtell or Ursula Sontheil] known as Mother Shipton. This version ending with the lines 'The world to an end shall come In eighteen hundred and eighty one.' was written by Charles Hindley in 1862.
    - Henry Busch letter to Reverend E. G. Brooks, 1891; AC.041.00015 (Box 41)
    - Megillah scroll, circa 19th -- 20th century; AC.039.00008 (Box 39)
      Top tray. Scroll is handwritten on parchment in Hebrew; the story of Queen Esther, Mordecai and King Ahasuerus, Persian King. The silver case is embellished with symbls of the Tuseves tribes.
    - Letters to Miss Lucie Gilliver, circa 1916 -- 1927; AC.041.00016 (Box 41)
    - Loose leaves from exhibit about history of writing, AC.052 (Box 42)
      Contains mainly printed leaves and facsimiles in Latin, Hebrew, and English, with one illuminated manuscript in Arabic.
  - Maps, circa 1586 -- 1947; AC.004.007
    This subseries contains printed and hand drawn maps dating circa 1586 – 1947. Most of the maps date from the 1800s and depict European countries. These maps also depict the African, Asian, European, North America, and South America continents as well various islands including the British Isles and East Indian Islands. Some maps of European and American cities can be found in this subseries, including printed and hand-drawn maps of the Tufts campus and the surrounding areas dating 1852 – 1947.
    - Map of Essex County, compiled from the latest Authorities by James G. Carter. Boston: Published by Carter and Hendee. [with Statistical Table of Essex County], 1830; AC.012.00005 (Box Small Map Case 2 Drawer 5)
      There are two copies of this map, one slightly damaged. The tag on the back of one of the maps gives the cataloging number 1552, the map was then dated via other cataloging numbers from the same period. These documents were found uncatalogued in the stacks in January 2009.
    - Maps, circa 1888 -- 1907; AC.027.00001 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 9)
      Inventory is as follows: ABC The Pathfinder Railway Guide Map Eastern Section. Rippey's Index Map of Lowell, Mass. 1888. Metropolitan Sewerage Commissioners, Plan of Charles and Neponset River Valleys Showing District to be Considered in Studies Relating to High Level Gravity Sewer Boston, Massachusetts 1899. Map of the City of Worcester 1902. Map of the City of Brockton 1889. Map of the Metropolitan Sewerage District Boston, Massachusetts September 30, 1899. Map of the City of Boston and Vicinity 1902. Clayton, New York 1903. Map of Newton. Map of the Fitchburg Hoosac Tunnel Route and Its Connections. ABC The Pathfinder Railway Guide Map Western Section. Supply and Distribution Systems of the Public Waterworks of Winchester, Mass. December 31, 1894. Map of Weymouth, Mass. 1907. City of Medford Map Showing Medford Sewerage System March 1, 1894. Metropolitan Sewerage Commissioners, Plan Showing Outlet of Nut Island, Recommended for High Level Gravity Sewer, Boston, Mass. 1899. Map of the City of Medford 1897. [Unlabeled: New Hampshire, Maine Railway Map]. [Unlabeled: Partial Pathfinder Eastern Seaboard].
    - Maps, circa 1676 -- 1900; AC.029.00001 (Box 29-30)
      This folder contains maps of the African, Asian, European, North American, and South American continents as well as maps of most of the European countries, Canada, India, the British Isles, and the East Indian Islands, dating circa 1782 -- 1877. There are also maps of cities such as Berlin, Delhi, London, New York City, and Pairs, dating circa 19th century. Of note in this folder are a map of the Americas dated 1676 and "A General Chart on Mercator's Projection to shew the Track of the Lion and Hindonstan from England to the Gulf of Pekin in China, and their return to England with the statement of the barometer and thermometer, containing also the limits of the Chinese Empire, as extended by the conquest of the present Emperor Chen-Lung (Quianlong)" dated circa 1735 -- 1796 (the reign of Quianlong).
    - Maps, circa 1586 -- 1760; AC.030.00002 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 8)
      Inventory is as follows: Map of west coast of Europe including the British Isles, undated. Map of the globe in French, circa 1760. Map of the globe in Latin circa 1742. "The Idle Prentice Executed at Tyburn" hand-colored print, circa 1747. Maps of England circa 1646 and 1650. Map of Spain circa 1586. Map of Scotland circa 1636 (Latin). Map of Italy circa 1682 (English). Map of the bay between Gravelines and Dunkirk, France, circa 1642.
    - Maps, circa 1780 -- 1947; AC.031.00001 (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 8)
      This folder contains maps with a few prints and some printed leaves dating circa 1780 – 1947. Most of the maps date from the 1800s and depict Europe and the United States. There are also maps of specific U.S. states such as Virginia and Maryland, and cities such as Boston, London, and Charlestown. There are also a few maps of British counties dating from 1947 as well as a map of Africa, undated. Of note in this folder are a map of Medford dated 1880 and a hand drawn map of Boston's western suburbs highlighting rivers and roads, undated.
    - Hand-drawn maps of the Mill pond area in Boston, MA and ship's log, circa 1803; AC.032.00003 (Box Large Map Case 1 Drawer 8)
  - Papyrus, circa 0100 -- 0850; AC.004.008
    This sub-series contains papyrus dating circa 0100 – 0850.
    - Papyrus, 0850; AC.011.00001 (Box 11)
    - Papyrus - Late Ptolemaic Egypt, AC.011.00019 (Box 11)
    - Papyrus, undated; AC.011.00020 (Box 11)
    - An example of Coptic writing on papryrus, Egypt, circa 0400 -- 0600; AC.020.00011 (Box 20)
      400-600 AD
  - Printed materials, 1478 -- 1893; AC.004.009